Wilford Wolfie Naman papers, Inclusive: 1892-1974, undated, Bulk: 1917-1919, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Wilford Wolfie Naman papers
Inclusive: 1892-1974, undated, Bulk: 1917-1919, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2128
Naman, William Wolfie, 1887 - 1978
2 document boxes.
The Wilford Wolfie Naman papers contain a variety of materials having to do with the activities of Wilford Wolfie Naman. Naman was a soldier during the First World War, and much of the collection is his wartime correspondence or other items relating to that conflict.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Poor.
Biography/Profile
Wilford Wolfie Naman was born to Jacob I. Naman and Fannie Cohen Naman on 1887 March 6 in Waco, Texas. Naman was the salutatorian of his high school class, graduating at the age of sixteen in 1903. Though Naman’s father worked in the cotton industry, there was no expectation that his son should join the family business. The semester following his graduation, Naman began taking classes at Baylor University. While at Baylor, Naman met Samuel Palmer (S. P.) Brooks, the President of the university. In his career, Brooks had spent two years at Baylor before moving on to Yale to finish his law degree. A great admirer of Brooks, Naman vowed to follow the same path. After two years at Baylor, Naman was accepted to Yale with no examinations required, and moved to Connecticut to begin classes. Upon his graduation, Naman moved back to Waco, Texas, in 1910, where he taught high school for one year before deciding to practice law.
In 1917 Naman helped to found Naman, Howell, Smith and Chase, a prominent law firm that still exists today under the name Naman, Howell, Smith and Lee. Upon the outbreak of the First World War in the spring of 1917, Naman enlisted in the National Guard. His unit was sent to Camp Bowie in Fort Worth in September of that year, where training began. Naman had drilled with the Baylor student military organization during his undergraduate years. As a lieutenant in the 131st Field Artillery, Naman shipped out to France with his unit in August of 1918. Naman was never on the front lines of the war, instead working as an artillery spotter. While on leave in Paris, he bought a fancy pair of boots that earned him the nickname “Beaucoup Boots.”
Naman came home from the war in the spring of 1919, where he resumed work in his legal practice. He married Isiadora Levy on 1923 February 12, and the couple had their only son, Jacob “Jay” Naman in 1925. Over the course of his professional career, Naman became a member of several different organizations, including the American Civil Liberties Union, the Ex-Students Association at Baylor, and the American Bar Foundation. He died on 1978 May 3, aged 91, and is buried at the Hebrew Rest Cemetery in Waco.
Scope and Content
The Wilford Wolfie Naman collection begins in 1892 and ends in 1974. The bulk of the collection dates from the later years of the First World War, 1917-1919. There are many undated items as well, primarily pieces of correspondence. The vast majority of the collection is in English, but one newspaper contains some articles in French. The largest series in the collection is Series I. Correspondence, which includes letters both sent and received by Wilford Wolfie Naman during the years 1917-1919. Much of the collection has connections to the First World War and Naman’s involvement in the conflict, however there are also links to the Texas legislature, the State Bar of Texas, and other personal connections to Naman himself.
Series I, Correspondence, features letters (filed chronologically). Series II, Photographic materials, features photographs and postcards. Series III, Legal documents, features deeds, legal correspondence, legislative booklets, and receipts. Series IV, Collected materials, features dance cards, trail logs, a diary, and booklets. Series V, Newspapers, features several newspapers pages (filed chronologically), as well as clippings and a magazine.
Arrangement
The collection came to us in original order, but with no discernible arrangement. The materials were in two document boxes, but there were no folders separating the items. For the current round of processing, some materials on the same topic were grouped together.
The collection is currently arranged into five series: I. Correspondence, II. Photographic Material, III. Legal Documents, IV. Collected Materials, V. Newspapers. The correspondence series is now arranged in chronological order.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2128.
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. "Wilford Wolfie Naman." Memorial #23250624. Databases. Accessed 2019 September 4.
Hoover, Carl. "Baylor Professor to share Waco's World War I memories in lecture." The Waco-Tribune, 2016 August 23.
Interview of Wilford Wolfie Naman by Thomas L. Charlton, Stephen Carsey, Gaines West, and Roger Sanders. Texas Judicial Systems Project, 1973 March 22 to September 3. Transcript, Baylor University Institute for Oral History, Waco, Texas.
Index Terms
Places
Waco (Tex.) -- History -- 20th Century.
Subjects
Ephemera.; Jews -- Texas -- Waco.; Lawyers -- Texas.; Newspapers.; Postcards.; Records (Documents); World War, 1914-1918.
Genres
Correspondence.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1890-1919, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Poor.
  Biography/Profile
  This series is made up of Wilford Wolfie Naman's correspondence, particularly letters, from the First World War. Most are written by Naman and sent home, however, some are written from his sister, Charlotte Birdie Naman Silvers (Mrs. Robert Silvers), or other friends and family to Naman. The series is in average condition.
  - Letters, 1890-1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters (1 of 2), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters (2 of 2), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters (1 of 4), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters (2 of 4), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters (3 of 4), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters (4 of 4), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters (1 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters (2 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters (3 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photographic material, 1918, undated; 2
  General condition: Average.
  This series contains postcards and photographs and is in average condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print; Postcards
  - Postcards and Photographs, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Legal documents, 1892-1974; 3
  This series contains receipts, tax records, warranty deeds, military promotion and movement records, a booklet from the Supreme Court of Texas and the State Democratic Executive Committee. The series is in poor condition.
  - Deeds, 1892-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Receipts, Military Records, and Legal Correspondence, 1905-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Collected materials, 1916-1920, undated; 4
  This series contains a dance card, a pistol manual, several opera playbills, Trail Logs of the 131st (2nd Texas National Guard) Field Artillery, a booklet concerning the Brazos River, a journal, and other materials collected by Wilford Wolfie Naman during his lifetime. The series is in average to poor condition.
  - General, 1918, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Booklets, 1916-1918, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Trail Logs (1 of 2), 1919 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Trail Logs (2 of 2), 1919 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Trail Logs, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Newspapers, 1909-1918; 5
  This series contains full newspapers, clippings, and a magazine. The series is in poor condition.
  - Newspaper Clippings and American Exporter, 1909-1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fort Worth Record Magazine of the War, 1917 October 21 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Stars and Stripes, 1918 October 25 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The New York Herald, 1918 November 4 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Waco-Tribune, 1918 November 11 (Box 2, Folder 12)